Inventory of the Academy For Educational Development Records, 1956-1986
Hoover Institution Archives
Academy For Educational Development Records,
1956-1986
82010
Academy For Educational Development
495 manuscript boxes, 6 oversize boxes (212 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches, memoranda, minutes, financial records, reports, studies, bulletins, photographs, phonotapes, and videotapes, relating to education in the United States, particularly higher education; education in underdeveloped countries; and the use of communications technology in education
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is stored off-site. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982 with subsequent increments.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
American nonprofit institution for promotion of planning in education.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, speeches, memoranda, minutes, financial records, reports, studies, bulletins, photographs, sound recordings, and video tapes, relating to education in the United States, particularly higher education; education in underdeveloped countries; and the use of communications technology in education.
Access Points
Developing countries.; Education.; Education--Developing countries.; Education--United States.; Educational technology.; United States.
Container List
- Aging. (Box No. 1-2.)
  - Florio, Carol, "Learning and the Older Adult: Education and Work Training Programs for Older Persons." DHEW Lifelong Learning Project. 1977, 377 (Box 1.)
  - "Never Too Old to Learn." Edna McConnell Clark Foundation. 1974, 196
  - Never Too Old to Learn. Edna McConnell Clark Foundation. 1974, 196.2
  - Scanlon, John, How to Plan a College Program for Older People, 1978, 196.3
  - Murphy, Judith, and Carol Florio, Never Too Old to Teach, 1978, 196.3
  - Florio, Carol, "1976 Survey of Collegiate Programs for Older Adults," 1977, 196.3
  - National Committee on Careers for Older Americans, Older Americans: An Untapped Resource, 1979, 371
  - "Final Report to the Edna McConnell Clark Foundation on the Status of the Program for the Elderly, Program Grants, and the Transition Plan," 1980, 4-371 (Box 2.)
  - Waring, Joan, The Middle Years: A Multidisciplinary View, 1978, 234.2
  - "Older Workers Emerge as Valuable Labor Resource." National Clearinghouse on Careers for Older Americans. 1980, 4-515
- Agency for International Development. (Box No. 2-9.)
  - General (Box 2.)
    - "Presentation to the Board of Directors," 1980, 2-000
    - Ingle, Henry T., Stephen F. Moseley, and Laurence Wolff, "Report on Preliminary Field Visits in Latin America to Identify Possible Major Planning Studies," 1974, 191.2
    - Leavitt, Howard B., and Peter L. Boynton, "Communications Technology for Development: Guidelines for Consultants Working with the Agency for International Development," 1976, 191.2
    - Chiappetta, Michael, Henry Ingle, John Arnaud, James Hoxeng, Jose Manduley, and Thereza Penna Firme, "A Report on the Project Planning Mission for the Use of Radio for Rural Development in Panama," 1975, 191.2
    - "Policy Options in Educational Technology: A Review of the Reports Prepared for Projects Funded by the Agency for International Development, 1967-1976," 1976, 191.2 (Box 3.)
    - Lalor, G. C., "Project Satellite." University of the West Indies. 1978, 312
    - Alter, Chester M., "Guidelines and Criteria for the Selection of University Contractors," 1967, 14
    - Silverman, Theresa, "Tele-Niger: Adapting an Electronic Medium to a Rural African Context." Clearinghouse on Development Communication Information Bulletin #8. 1976, 190
    - "Products and Services Produced by the Clearinghouse on Development Communication: September 1, 1976 to October 31, 1976," n.d., 190
    - Clearinghouse on Development Communication, "Summary Description of Activities," 1978, 190 (Box 4.)
    - Lester, Lois Joy, ed., A Directory of Sources of Assistance on Educational Technology for Development. Information Center on Instructional Technology. 1975, 190
    - Ingle, Henry T., Communication Media and Technology: A Look at their Role in Non-Formal Education Programs. Information Center on Instructional Technology Bulletin #5. 1974, 190
    - "Communications Strategies for Development," 1974, 190
    - Information Center on Instructional Technology, "Fourth Quarterly Report: June 1, 1975 to August 31, 1975," 1975, 190
    - Information Center on Instructional Technology, "Quarterly Reports: December 1, 1974 to February 28, 1975," 1975, 190
    - Information Center on Instructional Technology, "Quarterly Reports: September 1, 1973 to May 31, 1974," 1974, 190
    - Information Center on Instructional Technology, "Quarterly Report: June 1, 1976 to August 31, 1976," 1976, 190 (Box 5.)
    - Information Center on Instructional Technology, Instructional Technology Report. #1-16. 1972-1976, 190
    - Schramm, Wilbur, "ITV in American Samoa: After Nine Years," 1973, 190
    - Clearinghouse on Development Communication, "Project Profiles." Arabic edition. 1978, 190
    - Clearinghouse on Development Communication, "Project Profiles." French edition. 1978, 190
    - Clearinghouse on Development Communication, "Project Profiles." Spanish edition. 1978, 190
    - McAnany, Emile G., Radio's Role in Development: Five Strategies of Use. Clearinghouse on Development Communication Information Bulletin #4. 1973, 190
    - A Sourcebook on Radio's Role in Development. Clearinghouse on Development Communication Information Bulletin #7. 1976, 190
    - Gunter, Jonathan F., Super 8: The Modest Medium. UNESCO. 1976, 190
    - Ingle, Henry T., "The Use of Satellites for Telecommunication Systems in Education and National Development," 1974, 190 (Box 6.)
    - Clearinghouse on Development Communication, "Quarterly Report: September 1, 1976 to November 30, 1976, 1976, 190
  - El Salvador
    - Alter, Chester M., University Resources for International Development,1968, 60.1
    - McAnany, Emile G., John K. Mayo, and Robert C., 60.C
    - Hornik, "Television and Educational Reform in El Salvador." Research Report #4. 1970
    - Mayo, Judith A., "Teacher Observation in El Salvador." Research Report #5. 1971, 60.D
    - Merino de Manzano, Ana Maria, Robert C. Hornik, and John K. Mayo, "Feedback on Student Learning for Instructional Television in El Salvador." Research Report #6. 1971, 60.E
    - Speagle, Richard E., "Educational Reform and Instructional Television in El Salvador: Costs, Benefits, and Payoffs," n.d., 60.J (Box 7.)
    - Ingle, Henry T., Yolanda R. Ingle, Robert C. Hornik, John K. Mayo, Emile G. McAnany, and Wilbur Schramm, "Television and Educational Reform in El Salvador: Report on the Fourth Year of Research." Research Report #11. 1973, 60.K
    - Hornik, Robert C., Henry T. Ingle, John K. Mayo, Emile G. McAnany, and Wilbur Schramm, "Television and Educational Reform in El Salvador: Final Report." Research Report #14. 1973, 60.14
    - "The Creation of ODEPOR: The Office of Planning and Organizational Development in the Ministry of Education of El Salvador and the Development of a Work Program in Planning and Applied Studies,", 101.3
    - "Educational Programs in Music." Ministry of Education, El Salvador. 1973, 101.5
  - Guatemala
    - "The Basic Village Education Project in Guatemala," 1973, 139
    - "Basic Village Education Program in Guatemala," 1974, 139
    - Rich, Thomas A., Edgar G. Nesman, and Evaluation Staff, "The Basic Village Education Project (Programa de Educacion Basica Rural): Guatemala: Third Interim Report: Evaluation Component." University of South Florida. 1976, 175 (Box 8.)
    - University of South Florida, "Evaluation Report for Annual Review," 1975, 175
    - "The Basic Village Education Project (Programa de Educacion Basica Rural): Guatemala: Oriente Region: Combined Report, 1973-1976," 1977, 175
    - "The Basic Village Education Project (Programa de Educacion Basica Rural): Guatemala: Third Interim Report: Field Operations, June 1975-June 1976," 1976, 175
    - "The Basic Rural Education Project (Programa de Educacion Extraescolar): Guatemala: Second Annual Report, January 1977-December 1977," 1978, 175.3
  - Ivory Coast (Box 9.)
    - Grant, Stephen, Steven Klees, Frans Lenglet, and Emile McAnany, "Final Report: Economic Studies and Out-of-School Education Program Evaluation for the Ivory Coast," n.d., 255
- Communications/Instructional Technology/Media. (Box No. 9-15.)
  - "La Tecnologia Educativa y los Paises en Desarrollo: Un Manual." 1971, 75 (Box 9.)
  - "Technologie de l'Education et les Pays en Voie de Developpement: Un Manuel," 1971, 75
  - "Educational Technology and the Developing Countries: A Handbook," 1972, 75
  - Polcyn, Kenneth A., An Educator's Guide to Communication Satellite Technology, 1973, 75.2 (Box 10.)
  - Information Center on Instructional Technology, Information Bulletin. #1-4. 1972-1973, 75.3,4,5,6
  - Miller, James G., "Research and Development Priorities in Instructional Technologies for the Less Developed Countries." Report #1. 1973, 96.1
  - "Research and Development Priorities in Instructional Technologies for the Less Developed Countries: A Summary." Report #2. 1973, 96.2
  - Miller, James G., "Alternative Communications Systems for Education in the Less Developed Countries." Report #3. 1973, 96.3 (Box 11.)
  - Cowlan, Bert, Dean Jamison, Steven Klees, and Kenneth Polcyn, "Broadcast Satellites for Educational Development: Possible Key Decision Points, l973 to 1978." Report #4. 1973 to 1978.", 96.4
  - Cowlan, Bert, Dean Jamison, Kenneth Polcyn, Jai Singh, Delbert Smith, and Laurence Wolff, "Broadcast Satellites for Educational Development: The Experiments in Brazil, India, and the United States." Report #5. 1973, 96.5
  - Margolin, Joseph B., "Strategies for the Use of Communications Media in the Technologically Developing Nations." Report #6. 2 vols. 1973, 96.6 (Box 12.)
  - Rogers, Everett M., "Communications Strategies for Agricultural Development." Report #7. 1973, 96.7
  - "Reference Report: Analytical Services in Relating Communications Technology to Development," n.d., 96.8
  - Butman, Robert C., George W. Rathjens, and Colin J. Warren, "Technical-Economic Considerations in Public Service Broadcast Communications for Developing Countries." Report #9. 1973, 96.9 (Box 13.)
  - Agency for Instructional Television, "Career Development Education by Television," 1974, 203
  - Adler, Richard, and Walter S. Baer, Aspen Notebook: Cable and Continuing Education, 1973, 162
  - Rivers, William L., and William T. Slater, ed., Aspen Handbook on the Media: Research, Publications, Organizations, 1973, 162
  - Communications in the Americas Seminar, Stanford University, 1974. Proceedings, 201
  - Cater, Douglass, "Design for a Communications Media Council," 1971, 104
  - Gunter, Jock, "Elements of an Aid Strategy for Educational Radio in Latin America," n.d., 382 (Box 14.)
  - "The Jacksonville Newspapers: An Evaluation for the Florida Publishing Company," 1978, 449
  - Murphy, Judith, and Ronald Gross, Learning by Television, 1966, 10
  - "Present Status and Future Prospects for the Audiovisual Education Business: Prepared for Grolier Educational Corporation," 1969, -
  - "Helping Americans Learn about the World: A Study of Private-Sector Activities," 1978, 496
  - Schramm, Wilbur, and Lyle Nelson, "The Financing of Public Television," 1972, 123
  - "The Reporting of Human Behavior: A Study of Bridge- Building between Behavioral Sciences and Journalism." Russell Sage Foundation. 1970, 143
  - U.S. Commission on Instructional Technology, To Improve Learning: A Report to the President and the Congress of the United States, 1970, 57 (Box 15.)
  - Tickton, Sidney G., ed., To Improve Learning: An Evaluation of Instructional Technology. U.S. Commission on Instructional Technology. 2 vols. 1970-1971, 57
  - "Mainstreaming Gifted Handicapped Students into the Executive High School Internships Program," 1978, 363
- Countries. (Box No. 16-19.)
  - General (Box 16.)
    - "International Operations Division: An Overview," 1978 (2 copies)
  - Germany
    - "PREP Germany: An Analysis of the Predischarge Education Program at Army Posts in Germany." U.S. Department of the Army. 1973, 142.B
  - Guatemala
    - "The Basic Village Education Project (Programa de Educacion Basica Rural): Guatemala: Final Report." 1978, 175.2
    - Basic Village Education Seminar. Reports, 1978, 481
  - Iran
    - "Report to the Imperial Government of Iran, the Ministry of Roads and Transportation for Third Quarter of the Contract," 1976, 247
    - "The Educational Complex: Fourth Quarterly Report." Ministry of Roads and Transportation of Iran. 1976, 247
    - "The Educational Complex at Karadj: A Study," 1976, 247
    - "The Educational Complex at Loshan: A Study," 1976, 247
    - "Manpower and Training Needs Study." Ministry of Roads and Transportation of Iran. 1976, 247 (Box 17.)
    - "Framework Report for Institute of Operators and Maintainers to be Located at Loshan," 1976, 247
    - Leach, James L., "Educational Complex of the Ministry of Roads and Transportation, Imperial Government of Iran, Tehran, Iran: Operators and Maintainers Training Program," n.d., 247
    - Report in Persian. No translation. n.d., 247
    - Leach, James L., "Successful Instruction." Ministry of Roads and Transportation of Iran. n.d., 247
    - Millett, John D., "Observations about Higher Education in Iran." Ministry of Science Higher Education in Iran. 1976 (2 copies), 305
  - Korea (Box 18.)
    - "Expanding and Improving Programs of Education in Management in Korea." Ministry of Education of Korea. 1975, 222
    - "Future of Education for the Health Professions in Korea." Ministry of Education in Korea. 1975, 222
  - Puerto Rico
    - "Assumptions and Financial Projections: Inter-American University of Puerto Rico." 1973, 111.2
  - Saudi Arabia
    - Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, Educational Programming: Data Collection, Preliminary Studies and Analyses: Executive Summary. King Abdul Aziz University, Mecca Campus. 1976, 281.1
    - Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, Educational Programming: Data Collection, Preliminary Studies and Analyses. King Abdul Aziz University, Mecca Campus. 1976, 281.2
    - Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, "Meeting Papers: 11 and 12 September 1976: Jeddah." King Abdul Aziz University, Makkah Campus. 1976 King Abdul Aziz University, Mecca Campus. 1976, 281.3 (Box 19.)
    - Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, Educational Programming: Data Collection, Preliminary Studies and Analyses: Executive Summary., 281.4
  - United States
    - "PREP USA: An Analysis of the Predischarge Education Program at Army Posts in the Continental United States." U.S. Department of the Army. 1973, 142.A
    - "PREP USA Supplement: An Analysis of the Predischarge Education Program at Army Posts in the Continental United States." U.S. Department of the Army. 1973, 142.C
- Diplomatic/Negotiations. (Box No. 19-20.)
  - Gunter, Jonathan F., "The United States and the Debate on the World 'Information Order,'" n.d., 432.A,B (Box 19.)
  - Doob, Leonard W., ed., Resolving Conflict in Africa: The Fermeda Workshop,1970, 34
  - Druckman, Daniel, "Human Factors in International Negotiations," 1971, 34.1
  - "Observations on International Negotiations." 1971, 34.2 (Box 20.)
  - "Notes on Negotiating," 1972, 34.C
  - Communications Institute, "Communication and Conflict Program: Progress Report," 1976, 34.7
  - "Diplomats Reading and Cultural Program: Final Report." National Endowment for the Humanities. n.d., 37
- Management. (Box No. 20-27.)
  - Rauh, Morton A., The Advantages of Work-Study Plans, n.d., - (Box 20.)
  - Millett, John D., Allocation Decisions in Higher Education, n.d., -
  - Alternatives in State Government Financing of Higher Education. Council on Higher Education of the State of Washington. 1973, -
  - "A Deferred Cost of Education Plan for Podiatric Medicine." American Association of Colleges of Podiatric Medicine. 1976, 244
  - "Report of Consultants on AMA Periodicals," 1975, 236 (Box 21.)
  - Corporate Education Center, "Corporate Education Handbook for Upper-Level Executives," 1978, 398
  - The Contributions of Business Management to Higher Education Management. 1972 (2 copies), -
  - By 1990: Doubled Enrollments, Tripled Costs, n.d., -
  - Millett, John D., Confronting the New Depression in Higher Education: Two Budget Exercises, 1973, -
  - Millett, John D., Financing Current Operations of American Higher Education, 1972, - (Box 22.)
  - Millett, John D., Higher Education and the 1980s: Three Planning Papers, 1978, -
  - Behrens, Anna Jo W., Higher Education with Fewer Teachers: Some Examples of Current Practice, 1972, -
  - Gunter, Jock, and John Elmendorf, "Components of a Plan of Organizational Development for the Education Department of the Dominican Institute of Integral Education (IDEI)," 1976, 250.3
  - Wedemeyer, Charles, Ernest Gurule, and Jock Gunter, "Independent Study: Theory and Practice," 1975, 250.4
  - Management Forum. Vol. 1-3. 1972-1974, 102
  - Management Improvement Program, Ohio Board of Regents. Reports. 1973-1974, 102.1
  - Millett, John D., "A Critique of Current Organizational Structure: Wright State University." n.d., 268
  - "Roosevelt University: Kellogg Project Site Visit." 1978, 268 (Box 23.)
  - Kellogg Planning Project. Workshops, Chicago and St. Louis, 1977. Proceedings, l977, 268
  - "Planning in Higher Education: A Manual for Colleges and Universities." W. K. Kellogg Foundation. 1977, 268
  - Millett, John D., ed., "Planning in Higher Education: A Manual for Colleges and Universities." W. K. Kellogg Foundation. 1977, 268
  - "Essentials of a Management Information System." n.d., 268
  - "Observations on International Negotiations," 1971, 173 (Box 24.)
  - Let's End the Confusion about Simulation Models! A Summary of a Candid Discussion of their Place in Higher Education. Society for College and University Planning. 1973, -
  - Internationalizing Management Education. Advisory Committee on Business and International Education, U.S. National Commission for UNESCO. 1973, 113.2
  - Millett, John D., Mergers in Higher Education: An Analysis of Ten Case Studies, 1976 (2 copies), -
  - "The Naropa Institute." Foundation for the Realization of Man. 1975, 240
  - "NCJW at 85: Directions and Projections." National Council of Jewish Women. 1979, 473
  - "A Guide for Planning and Selecting the Site for the National Academy for Fire Prevention and Control." National Fire Prevention and Control Administration. 1975, 253
  - "A Guide for Planning and Selecting the Site for the National Academy for Fire Prevention and Control." National Fire Prevention and Control Administration. 1975 (2d copy), 253 (Box 25.)
  - Millett, John D., An Outline of Concepts of Organiza- tion, Operation, and Administration for Colleges and Universities. 1974, -
  - Personnel Management in Higher Education, 1972, -
  - Millett, John D., Politics and Higher Education.1974, -
  - Irwin, Judith, ed., "A Guide to Professional Development Opportunities," 1973, -
  - "A Guide to Professional Development Opportunities for College and University Administrators," 1971, -
  - Sullivan, George, ed., "A Guide to Professional Development Opportunities for College and University Administrators," 1972, -
  - Irwin, Judith T., ed., "A Guide to Professional Development Opportunities for College and University Administrators," 1974, - (Box 26.)
  - Irwin, Judith T., ed., "A Guide to Professional Development Opportunities for College and University Administrators," 1975, -
  - Schwenkmeyer, Barry, and Mary Ellen Goodman, ed., Putting Cooperation to Work, 1972, -
  - Reinert, Paul C., Rescue Begins at Home, 1972, -
  - Tickton, Sidney G., "The Effect of Unemployment Insurance Costs on the Public Schools." National Institute of Municipal Law Officers. 1978, 414
  - Millett, John D., Strengthening Community in Higher Education, 1974, -
  - Hruby, Norbert J., A Survival Kit for Invisible Colleges, or: What to Do Until Federal Aid Arrives, 1973, -
  - Survival through Change: A Case Study of a Privately Supported Urban University's Plan to Fight the Budget Squeeze, n.d., -
  - Shoemaker, William A., Systems, Models and Programs for Higher Education: A Catalogue, 1973, -
  - 319 Ways Colleges and Universities Are Meeting the Financial Pinch, n.d., -
  - "Report to the Urban Mass Transportation Administration, Department of Transportation, on the Feasibility of Establishing an UMTA-University Advisory Committee for the University Research and Training Grants Program and Recommendations for the Strengthening of UMTA-University Relationships," 1972, 119 (Box 27.)
- National Institute of Health/Office of Education/National Science Foundation. (Box No. 27-29.)
  - "Present Planning for Higher Education." National Institutes of Health. 1967, 21 (Box 27.)
  - Eurich, Alvin C., Lucien B. Kinney, and Sidney G. Tickton, "The Expansion of Graduate and Professional Education during the Period 1966 to 1980." National Institutes of Health. 1969, 22
  - Mayhew, Lewis B., "Long Range Planning for Higher Education." National Institutes of Health. 1969, 23
  - Murphy, Judith, and Ronald Gross, The Arts and the Poor: New Challenge for Educators. U.S. Office of Education. 1968, 27
  - "Continuing Education in the United States: A New Survey." National Institutes of Health. 1971, 38
  - Tickton, Sidney G., and Sherwood Davidson Kohn, "The New Instructional Technologies: Are They Worth It?" 1971, 42 (Box 28.)
  - "Study of the Feasibility of Establishing a National Planning Congress for Higher Education." U.S. Office of Education. 1969, 58
  - "National Planning for Education." U.S. Office of Education. 1970, 58
  - Abrahams, Louise, "State Planning for Higher Education." U.S. Office of Education. 1969, 58
  - Howe, Harold, II, The People Who Serve Education. U.S. Office of Education. 1968, 62
  - "Examining the Feasibility of Extending Postsecondary Educational Opportunity." 1969, 74.1
  - "Toward Universal Postsecondary Educational Opportunity," 1969, 74.2
- Other Institutions/Associations/Commissions. (Box No. 29-30.)
  - "Strategies for Reform," 1972, 129 (Box 29.)
  - "The Education Professions Annual Report: Focus 1973: The Elementary and Secondary Levels of Education." U.S. Office of Education. 1973, 137
  - "Area Studies on U.S. Campuses: A Directory." World Studies Data Bank. 1974, 136.3
  - Advisory Panel on the Grants Program of the Association of College and Research Libraries, "Final Report," 1969, -
  - "Directory of University Programs." World Studies (University) Data Bank. 3 vols. 1973, 136
  - "A Report to the Board of Trustees on the International Museum of Photography at George Eastman House, Rochester, New York," 1980, 1-672